[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, so you often... you often see the suttas... in the suttas, contentment being mentioned as something to develop, as something to... to cultivate and... and protect.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question there really is, what kind of attitude do you have towards your own contentment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it something you regard as...
[SPEAKER_00]: As given, just sort of, that you're not responsible for, as, you know, you can't help it, whether you're contented or discontented, or is it something that you can actually make the effort towards, protect it, develop it further, make it increase, if it's sort of not that present.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole point is to recognize that actually it is something you can do, and it's something you can
[SPEAKER_00]: Learn how to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as the suttas often often mention it, it is something you can cultivate, and it's actually necessary for practice, because content and discontent are rooted in the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're states of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not dependent on the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, sure, sometimes circumstances are absolutely not conducive for the practice, and you should not be content with those.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the time will come where there is no particular external reason for your discontent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, everything is fine, health is fine, you have enough food, seclusion, you're not being overwhelmed by the elements and so on, by things you have to deal with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the mind is not content.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is restless, the mind is looking for
[SPEAKER_00]: Different things, change of the environment and so on, and that's what you need to recognize then, that that's the problem now, that the mind cannot be contented with things that are actually suitable for the goal that you are clear about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether a monk or a layperson, you should always be reviewing your situation as if it's... Is it still supporting for the practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it still supporting for the precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it too challenging?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it making things too tempting, too hard to uphold?
[SPEAKER_00]: If things are not going in the direction of making your life harder, making a practice harder, then you should also keep an eye on your mind, so it does not become discontented with things that are otherwise fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... that's why contentment is deep down, it's actually learned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, fundamentally, the mind that's, eh... that has developed more, can be contented even with things, you know, even with like a loss of health and so on, because, eh... as I said, it is rooted in the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The state of mind that doesn't, eh... doesn't resist, that's fundamentally what contentment is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do wanna... and then, it means you're basically at ease and in a state of equilibrium regardless of what you're going through.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why contentment should... could also be made into like a goal to strive for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will be contented with things internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and even if sometimes you choose to, say, change the environment, because maybe it ceased to be suitable for the practice, and you you see it directly, how it relates to, you know, the lack of progress, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even then, you can remain contented internally, even with the change, even with with with acting towards the change that is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can be contented.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contented with uncertainty, contented with lack of control.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things are pretty much come down on the level of that... accepting them on the level of your mind and not necessarily ignoring them or just pretending to go with the flow or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you might sometimes have to interrupt the flow, sometimes you might have to do things and so on, but either way, whether you're with the flow or against it, in terms of your environment, you should be contented internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the clearer the nature of things become, the nature of change, unknown ability and so on, the more effortlessly contented you would be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being contented with little, with fewness of desires, with seclusion and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these goals towards the developing a certain type of environment, such as, you know, not socializing and chasing centrality, keeping the precepts, you need to learn how to be contented with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, the mind wants to go with the pull of desires and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, once you do establish environment on the basis of your discernment, such as, oh, this environment is good for me, this environment is good for practice, does not necessarily make me feel inspired or pleasant, because solitude is hard if it's not learned, abstaining from pursuing essential desires is hard if it's not developed and so on, but
[SPEAKER_00]: I will sustain it, and then I will learn how to be contented with that, and that's where the practice will take a whole new level.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the kind of, you know, finding joy, learning how to find joy in solitude and non-sensuality and joys of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not going to happen automatically or naturally or something, because naturally, sensuality is the direction the mind wants to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Company is the direction the mind wants to go, and that's why you're liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, going against that grain is something you first need to take on, out of faith, out of understanding, out of intellectual understanding, that it is something that can result in greater good for yourself and others, such as liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you actually have to learn how to be contented with and protect that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said in the beginning, just don't confuse that for learning to ignore things that are not suitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should not be contented with sensuality and you should not be contented with the environment that's conducive to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should not be contented with socializing, depending on other people for your emotional support.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not something you should be contented with, because that is very much rooted in suffering, and it's certainly perpetuating the basis that is making you liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Learn to be contented with things that you know are conducive for peace, for dispassion, for disenchantment, for seclusion, for liberation, pretty much, for non-dependence on any external or internal factor, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the goal to be contented with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah, sometimes you probably have to, you know, you will catch yourself whereby
[SPEAKER_00]: Things are very conducive for practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing... there's nothing you have to deal with or address.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you find your mind in a state of discontent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You find your mind in a state of... not being settled or happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: And all you need to do then is just, you know, make some effort and contemplate the reasons for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, not look for faults, but look for the reasons for mind being discontent in the environment that's otherwise, you know, quite suitable for content.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, actually, yeah, just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Refrain from those thoughts that would be fueling the discontent, such as, as I said, looking for faults, finding negative in... irrationally finding negative in things around you that are not otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and then just sustain that awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Endure that awareness that the mind is in a state of discontent, while there is no reason for it to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said, make sure you don't welcome that discontent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fuel it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think on account of it carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will have to fade, because it does require... that irrational discontent requires equally irrational maintenance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to be providing support.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to be providing
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts that are adding more to that context of discontent, don't... don't give in to that irrational fault finding.
[SPEAKER_00]: That has to be the basis for discontent, pretty much always.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it's not a factual basis for discontent, such as unsuitable environment, then it would be your own fault-finding mind that would be the reason for discontent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always, you know, thinking, oh, well, it will be better like this or better like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no end to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's a kind of a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mara's daughter's trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Suttas would say, discontent is one of the ways to basically fall away from the wholesome, skillful context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're in a very skillful environment, and then keep living, basically, in a very, very unskillful framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might still be restrained, and so on, and not engaging with centrality and secluded, but if, fundamentally, on top of that, the mind does not develop the framework of contentment, that will be blocking the progress, that will be preventing the context from that fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even in the in a layman's setting, obviously, you know, with its own limitations, you can still, on the basis of your precepts, recognize what environment is suitable for the precepts, and then try and uphold such environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will make your restraint and renunciation
[SPEAKER_00]: easier, or at least more sustainable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, don't think your work ends there either, because the mind will not necessarily, even if you do it, even if you protect your environment, even if you keep your own precepts, the mind will not necessarily
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you do sustain your effort, and as I said, if you then become aware of your gratuitous discontent, then you can actually slowly learn how to experience the pleasure of enunciation, which is what contentment is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually start to prefer renunciation, precepts, seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, even within the limited framework of a lay setting, still, the contentment is necessary to be developed upon the right and skillful behavior that you've been cultivated beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you become contented with such lifestyle, then, obviously, the pressure of sensuality that goes against that lifestyle, the pull of society, the company, will lessen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are actually preferring the opposite now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not just, you know, through a determination and inspiration, making the effort to go against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're becoming quite contented, quite happy in living against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the practice becomes more effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, that can be developed even further and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why contentment is important as a mental factor.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, that's why often the Buddha would talk about it, because it is something that everybody will have to address at some point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't just expect mind to be contented on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if it is contented on its own, you still need to do the work and review it and check.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there contentment there because of the true recognition that this environment is good for me and my sense of restraint is supported and renunciation is supported?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, are you contented just because, you know, there's some central basis or something that the mind is actually still delighting in, and you're confusing that for the right type of contentment?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether the mind is contented or not, you need to keep reviewing whether the mind is contented or not, and the reasons for that contentment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it's... if they're suitable and wholesome and skillful, sure, you protect, you keep... you keep... you keep being aware of that context, but if they're not, that's where you kind of rewrite them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you prevent your mind from dwelling on the negative aspects or the central aspects and try to basically replace them with a wholesome contemplations and skillful aspects that basically would be revolving around renunciation and learning how to like it, pretty much, in plain terms.